<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Declaration of the lyfe and death of Iohn Story, late a Romish canonicall doctor, by professyon</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1571</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22577610</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22577610</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13004)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1758:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Declaration of the lyfe and death of Iohn Story, late a Romish canonicall doctor, by professyon</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Colwell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1571.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within illustrated border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the St. John's College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Story, John, 1510?-1571.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25619:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25619:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>TA</p>
               <p>·PRVDENTIA·</p>
               <p>·DIEV·ET·MON·DROIT·</p>
            </figure>
            <p>A declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lyfe and Death of <hi>Iohn Story,</hi> Late a Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall Doctor, by profeſſyon. 1571.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, by Thomas Colwell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25619:2"/>
            <head>¶The ſpeciall Contents of this declaration.</head>
            <list>
               <item>First, wherfore Iohn Story was impriſoned in the Queenes Benche.</item>
               <item>His breaking of that Priſon and flyeng into Flaunders.</item>
               <item>His trayterous and naughtie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng there.</item>
               <item>The cauſe and maner of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyance from thence into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</item>
               <item>The maner of his arainement, and Iudgement.</item>
               <item>The maner of his death and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution.</item>
               <item>An Epilogue or ſhort concluſion of his Lyfe.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25619:2"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader in this ſhort declaration, I purpoſe briefely to note vnto thee, part of the life and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of death of Iohn Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, late a Romiſh &amp; Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Doctor by profeſſion. If I ſhould diſcourſe the common places of diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of perſones, his parentes, hys educatyon and bringyng vp, hys ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie outragious doinges executed by him in the perſecutynge of the membres of Chriſt, &amp; the maner of his life from time to time, namely in the time of K. Henry the eight, when the ſtatute of ſixe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles was firſt ſet foorth, &amp; all his crueltie vſed ſithens, to the daye of his death: it woulde aſke a volume as greate as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> booke of Martyrs: a great part of which booke is ſtuffed with his tirannous and cruell tragedies, executed againſt God and his poore membres.</p>
               <p>As for the wilfull and wicked courſe of his yonger yeres, a great parte wherof he ſpent in the Vniuerſitie of Oxford<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to reporte all the partes, it would requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e a longe ſtorie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25619:3"/>
               <p>One Pranke may ſtand in ſtead of many. And although Chriſtian charitie requyre vs alwaye, and of all men, to reporte the beſt, ſpeciallye of them that be departed: Yet no charytie forbyddeth a man with ſobryetie and modeſtye to reporte the truethe for the benefite of good example to other: Or els all writyng of hiſtories after the parties death (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be moſt truely written) ſhould bee condemned, &amp; the bridle of iuſt infamy perilouſly taken away from wicked men.</p>
               <p>About the yere of our Lord. 1529. Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie beinge a ſtudent of the ciuill lawe in Hinkſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Hall in Oxforde, and on a time lodging abroade alone as often tymes his maner was to do, in the company of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whome hee had at his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, was fet home from thence late in the night, and caried alofte through the open ſtreetes with a ſolemne proceſſion of the whole companie of his houſe, euery man caryenge a candell burninge before hym, as a token of hys virginytye, and ſyngyng merelye together,
<q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:25619:3"/>
                     <l>Qui pius, prudens, humilis, pudicus,</l>
                     <l>Sobrius, caſtus fuit, &amp; quietus,</l>
                     <l>Vita dum preſens. &amp;c.</l>
                  </q> as if they had ben S. Nicholas clerkes.</p>
               <p>After that, about the yere of our Lord, 1538. the ſayde Storye beyng then Doctour and Pryncypall of Broadgates in the ſayde vniuerſytie of Oxforde, and miſtruſtinge a yonge gentleman for ouer familiar reſorting to his aquaintaunce in the towne, gaue him earneſt charge, with terrible threates, as he loued his life to come there no more, for Loue &amp; Lordſhip can brooke no fellowſhipp.</p>
               <p>Therfore on a certayne tyme for hys good chaſte purpoſe, takynge occaſion to walke abroade, and hauing his man with his ſworde wayting vppon him, &amp; paſſing through the Church yarde of S. Olaues he met the ſayde yonge gentle man retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning home from the towne, beeyng vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly without weapon, &amp; hauing onlie his ſtudy gowne caſt vpon him. And he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that he cam from ſuch places as he had ſo often for bidden him, in great furie and heate of minde, being alſo fired with ieloſie towards his loue, he raught backe ſodenlye vnto hys man and drewe hys
<pb facs="tcp:25619:4"/> ſworde, &amp; hauing the gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in the corner of two walles, ran him thorowe both ſydes, &amp; lefte him for dead.</p>
               <p>Imediatly a cry was rayſed, the people aſſembled, Doctour Storye was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the officers, &amp; layd in Bocardo: wher he continued vntill it was perfectly knowen, that the yonge gentleman ſo wounded was paſt all danger. For God by hys gracyous prouydence ſo dyrected the ſworde, that notwithſtanding it pear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced through both ſides, yet it periſhed not one parte of all the entrailes.</p>
               <p>Hee that writeth theſe wordes is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hereof and ſawe the partye dreſſed, &amp; the towells drawen through his bodie. The partie ſo wounded is named N. Brierton, and is yet aliue.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the fyrſt fruites of Doctour Stories good Doctorly doinges, agreable with his lyfe that folowed after warde.</p>
               <p>A kyndly beare wyll bite by tyme.</p>
               <p>Now I wyll begyn the reſt of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration at the begynnyng of the Reigne of the moſt vertuous, godly, learned and hopeful Prince, King Edward the ſixt: who after the death of the moſt noble
<pb facs="tcp:25619:4"/> and famous prince, Kinge Henrye the .viii. his Father, tooke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, as of right appertayned vnto him, the Regall ſtate and gouernment of this Realme. And firſt, and before all other thinges, he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge the high aduauncement of Goddes honour reſtored vnto vs the ſincere do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and made moſt Godly Lawes for the abholyſſhynge of all ſuperſtycion and idolatry. At whiche tyme, Iohn Storye being then of the Parlyament houſe and a great enemye to the gloryous light of Chriſtes Goſpel, did vehemently inueigh agaynſt the godly doynges of that vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, namely, for ſettynge foorth the booke of Common Prayer and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtracion of the Sacraments in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh: where he did not only ſlaunderouſlye ſpeake of the Doctrine, but alſo malyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſediciouſlye ſpake of that godly Prince (alleging the ſentence of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes: <hi>That wo is to that Realme whoſe kynge is but a childe,</hi> wreſtynge the ſame text againſt that noble Prince, euen to the ſame ſence that gaue cheefe occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the rebellion in the ſame kinges tyme, and meaning that both the Prince &amp; the
<pb facs="tcp:25619:5"/>realme did they wyſt not what.</p>
               <p>And ſhortly after that he had thus decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his rebellious hart &amp; canckred iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he then fledde this realme into the parties beyond the ſeas, and there abode all the life of that vertuous Prince.</p>
               <p>After his death, as ſone as the late Queene Mary poſſeſſed the crowne, the aforſayd Story retorned agayne from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, and obtayned of Queene Mary by the helpe of Biſhop Boner, that he became a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioner, and a cruell per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſecutor of Chriſtes members, wherin he traueyled with ſuch vehemency and in ſuch a tyrannous maner, as neuer was there any before him did, and in that ſtate he contynued all the dayes of Queene Maryes lyfe.</p>
               <p>After the death of Queene Mary, ſo ſone as our moſt dere ſoueraigne Lady came to the poſſeſſion of the crowne, and that ſhe had called a parliament, chieflye for the reſtitution of Gods bleſſed worde and the true adminiſtracion of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to Goddes high honor, and alſo for the amendment of the decayed ſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:25619:5"/> this Realme. The ſaid Storie beyng of the parliament houſe who was an enemy to all godly reformations, did wyth great vehemency ſpeake agaynſt the bill that was therexhibited for the reſtytucyon of the booke of common prayer, &amp; ſayd theſe wordes: I did often times in Queene Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries tyme, ſaye to the Biſhops that they were to buſie with <hi>Pecora campi,</hi> (for ſo it pleaſed him to terme the poore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) chopping at twiges, but I wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to haue chopped at the roote, which if they had done, this gere had not cum now in queſtion, and here in moſt traiterouſly he ment the diſtruccion of our dere &amp; ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne lady Queene Elizabeth. For the which wordes ſpoken in ſuch an audience and in ſuch vehement maner, there was no honeſt nor true hart that hard him but did vtterly abhorre him.</p>
               <p>And ſone after that he had declared his trayterous hart to the Queenes highnes, and his conſcience accuſing him, he fled and lurked about in ſondry corners, as did Cain when he had murdered his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abell. But at the laſt he was taken in the weſt countrye rydyng before a
<pb facs="tcp:25619:6"/> Male in a friſe coate lyke a ſeruing man, and was apprehended in the highwaie by one maiſter Ayleworth a gentleman one of the Queenes ſeruauntes, and brought before the counſaill, and after ſent to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the Queenes Bench (for more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſpicion of Treaſon) in the fyrſt yere of her highnes reigne.</p>
               <p>And after the ſayd Story had remained there a whyle he eſpyenge hys tyme and by the helpe of his frendes (as commonly ſuche lewde papiſtes lacke none) he brake the ſaid priſon and fled againe beyond the Seas, namely into Flaundyrs, and there not only practiſed diuerſe wicked &amp; trey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous enterprices towardes our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne lady the Quenes maieſtie and the ſtate of this realme, by ſondry co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferences that he had with ſuch as haue of late rebel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpired the deſtruccion of the ſame. But alſo he became an open &amp; comon ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mi to euery good ſubiect of this realme of England, and obteyned in Flaundyrs of the Duke of Alna a comiſſion and auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to practiſe his olde cruetie &amp; to areſt &amp; aprehend al ſuch Engliſhmens goods as ſhold arriue in thoſe countries, or that did
<pb facs="tcp:25619:6"/> traffique out of England into thoſe parts, or from thence into England, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame by reaſon of which aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he vſed there ſuch extremytie that he was the ſpoiler &amp; vndoer of dyuerſe mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chauntes, and of more would haue bene, if he had longer continued: wherfore the ſaid Merchauntes were in forced to ſtudy and deuyſe ſome remeady, and to practiſe ſome waye or meane howe to remoue this comber ſome man from them.</p>
               <p>And among other deuiſes, they hauing experience of hym to be a gredy and raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous wolfe, put into his head (by ſuch as he ſuſpected not) that ther was a pray for hym of Engliſh goodes in a Ship that lai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in a certein place which was named vnto him, where he ſhould fynd ſuch a treaſure of goods to be confiſcate, as woulde be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficient for him during his life. The wolfe beynge hongry and deſyrous of this great pray, ſet forward, and came into a Shyp that promyſed to brynge hym to the place where the praye was. But to be ſhorte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſone as he was entered the Shipe, the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e brought hym cleane a waye out of Flaundirs into England, and landed him
<pb facs="tcp:25619:7"/> at Harwyche in the Moneth of Auguſte laſt paſte.</p>
               <p>And ſone after, knowlege being geuen to the Queenes honorable counſail of his landynge, he was brought to London and there he was comitted to priſon to the lol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lardes tower in Powles where he conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a whyle that he myght well peruſe that place wherin he had moſt cruelly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented many a good Chryſtyan. But he lacked there one thing, which was the monſtrous and houge Steckes, that hee and Boner his old faithfull frend had vſed to turmoyle and perſecute the poore and Innocent chriſtians in, hanging ſum ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in by the heles ſo high, that only their hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des laye on the ground. Some wer ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in both feet &amp; armes, ſome alſo wer ſtocked by both their feet and by both thir thombes, and ſo did hang in the Stockes. And ſome alſo were ſtocked by both theyr fete, &amp; cheyned by the necke wyth collars of Iron made faſt behynde theim to a poſt in the wall, and ſuche other deueliſhe and tyrannus engynes and deuyſes by hym practiſed theſe at his being in the lolardes Tower he myſſed, and great pitie it was
<pb facs="tcp:25619:7"/> that he had not taſted of theim: But alack the good Biſſhop Gryndall late Byſſhop of London had brent and conſumed them with fire.</p>
               <p>But to returne where I left, after that Story had contynnued a certaine of tyme in the lollardes Tower, &amp; had ben diuers tymes examined, hee was from thence remoued to the Tower of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, wher he remayned vntill the .xxvi. day of Maye. 1571. And then was he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought from thence into weſtminſter hall before the iudges of the Queenes Benche, and there arayned. And after the indictment had ben read vnto hym, theffect wherof was, that wher as Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Norton, Thomas Markenfelde, Chriſtopher Neuyll, Frances Norton &amp; Thomas Ienny alias Iennings with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther traytors, after their offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the north; and being therof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted in the .xii. yere of the Queenes highnes raigne before the right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Thomas Erle of Suſſex lorde preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Queenes cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaill in the north partes, Iohn lorde Darcye &amp;c. they after
<pb facs="tcp:25619:8"/> their indictment did the .xxiii. of Iune in the yere aforſayd embarke theim ſelues in ſundry Shippes and fled this realme vnto Antwarpe in Brabant, whych is vnder the gouernment of kyng Phylip, and ther contrarye to theyr allegeaunce did lead their liues, and the aforſaid Iohn Story. D. W. P and I. P, being borne in England and the Queenes ſubiectes, did with theim conſpire, compaſſe and Imagin the Queenes death, and her high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to depoſe and depryue.</p>
               <p>And by diuers perſwaſions and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters did alſo procure ſtraungiers to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade this realme of England, and to leuy warr againſt the Queene, and her hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to depoſe. And that the aforſayd Iohn Story &amp;c. knowing the aboueſaid Norton and others to haue committed their treaſons here in England, did rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort and helpe theim at Antwarp aforſaid, agaynſt their allegeaunce. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And after the indictment read he being called vppon by the courte to anſwere to the ſame, pleaded that he was not the Queenes ſubiect nor had not bene theſe
<pb facs="tcp:25619:8"/> vii. yeres, but was the ſubiect of the moſt catholicke and mighty prynce kyng Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip kyng of Spayne, to whome hee was ſworne, and had in Fee of him one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth pound by the yere, therfore ſaid hee I am not bound to anſwer to that indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neyther will I anſwere vnto it.</p>
               <p>And here he vſed many pretie tauntes as well to the iudges as alſo pleaſyng him ſelfe with giuinge of pretie nippes and girdes.</p>
               <p>And verye ſtowtlye, he maintayned his former plea, affirming alſo, that they were not his lawfull iudges, neither that they had law to procede againſt him being none of the Queenes ſubiectes.</p>
               <p>And then beyng demaunded where he was borne? he anſwered in England.</p>
               <p>Then ſayd they it folowith that you are ſubiect to the lawes of thys realme, and ſhould be ſo to our Queene</p>
               <p>Wherunto he replyed and ſayd, that God commaunded Abraham to go foorth from the lande and countrey where he was borne, from his friendes and kynſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke into another countrey. And ſo he folowynge his example, for conſcience
<pb facs="tcp:25619:9"/> ſake in religion did forſake his country<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the lawes of this realme &amp; the prince alſo, and had wholy geuen hym ſelfe to the ſeruice of a foreyne gouernour kyng Philip kyng of Spayne.</p>
               <p>And herevpon hee ſtood very ſtoutlye, but to ſmall purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Then when hee perceaued that they would procede in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt him, he ſayde, they had no lawe ſo to do. And with that he turned him about to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſayd: good people, I truſt ye ſee howe violently I am vſed and howe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly and contrary to all iuſtice and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie they vſe mee.</p>
               <p>And he added that he had good hope that he was not deſtitute of ſome frendes there that would geue notice and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege to the moſt Catholycke prynce hys maiſter how cruelly they dealt with him.</p>
               <p>And then againe, beyng called vppon to anſwere, one ſayd vnto him, maiſter Storye, becauſe you thynke it violence that is ſhewed vnto you in ſtead of lawe and iuſtice, you ſhall knowe that wee do nothyng but that wee maye do both by lawe and equitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25619:9"/>
               <p>And then one of the Iudges ſaid: this is Scarborowes caſe. Nay, ſaid Story, my caſe is not Skarboroughes caſe: but in déede I had Skarborough warnynge to come to this arraignement, for I knewe nothynge therof vntyll .vij. of the clocke in the mornynge.</p>
               <p>Then, there was a booke delyuered hym to read, wherin he might ſée what they might doo by lawe: and after hée had read it, the Iudge demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of him how he liked it? And he anſwered, God haue mercie vpon mée. Then the Lorde chyefe Iuſtice gaue him Iudgement to be drawen, hanged and quartred, and ſo was he agayne ſent vnto the Tower.</p>
               <p>And as he went by the way: certayne perſons in ſeuerall places met with him and one ſaid: Oh Story, Story: thou art a ſtrange Story: Remember Mayſter Bradforde that godly man, his blood aſketh vengeaunce on thée Story: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in time. Another cryed on hym and ſaid: Story, call to mynde the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour that thou ſhewedeſt vpon Maiſter Read, a Gentleman, whom thou diddeſt vtterly deſtroye: aſke God forgeueneſſe Story for that wicked déede.</p>
               <p>Another cryed vnto hym and ſaide:
<pb facs="tcp:25619:10"/> Bleſſed be God, Story, that hath made thée partaker of ſuche Breade, as thou waſt wont to deale to the innocent membres of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Another alſo cryed out vpon him, and ſaide: Story, Story: the abhominable cup of fornication and filthynes that thou haſt geuen other to drinke, be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vp topfull, that thy plagues maye be the greater at the terrible daye of Gods wrath &amp; vengeaunce, vnleſſe thou aſke mercy for thy filthy, corrupte &amp; ſtinkyng lyfe. And yet agayne, another cryed out vnto hym and ſaid: I pray God that thy hart be not hardened, as was Pharaos, and made harder then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Adamant ſtone, or the ſtéele, that when he woulde, he could not repent and call for grace.</p>
               <p>And among al the reſt, one came to him at London Stone, and ſaluted him with this Méeter, ſaiyng:
<q>
                     <l>Maiſter Doctor Story,</l>
                     <l>For you they are right ſory</l>
                     <l>The Court of Louaine and Rome:</l>
                     <l>Your holy father the Pope,</l>
                     <l>Cannot ſaue you from the rope,</l>
                     <l>The Hangman muſt haue your gown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To whom he anſwered not one word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25619:10"/>
               <p>THe firſt daye of Iune, the ſaide Story was drawen vpon an her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell from the Tower of London vnto Tiborn: wher was prepared for him a newe payre of Gallowes made in triangle maner. And by the way as he went, many people ſpake vnto hym, and called vpon hym to repent his Tir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie and wickednes, and wylled him to call vpon God for mercy: But he lay as though he had ben a ſleepe, &amp; woulde not ſpeake to any perſon.</p>
               <p>And when he was taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the herdell and ſet in a carte, he made there a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne proteſtation, and ſaid:</p>
               <p>¶I am come hither to die: and truely, if this death were ten times more fierce and ſharpe then it is, I haue deſerued it?</p>
               <p>I haue lyued the ſpace of thréeſcore &amp;. vij. yeres: and now my body muſt abyde this temporall payne and puniſſhement prouyded for mée here in this lyfe, by meane wherof, my daies ſhalbe cut off.
<pb facs="tcp:25619:11"/>But where at the firſt I ſtoode in feare of death, I thanke God, this night paſſed I haue ben ſo comforted with good and godly men, that the feare of death is taken from my ſight. And nowe I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to God the Father, truſtyng in the Paſſion of his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, and hopynge, by the ſheding of his blood only to be ſaued. And althoughe of a longe time I coulde not applie the vertue of his Paſſion and death to the vſe &amp; bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of my ſoule, becauſe of my longe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerynge in feare: Yet nowe, I thanke God, I know how to applye this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyne, as for example:</p>
               <p>A Pothecarye maye haue a Medicine liyng in his ſhop .vij. yeares, that maye helpe a ſicke or diſeaſed man by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle of a Phyſicion: But if this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyne be not applyed to the pacient, but ſtyl remaineth in the Apothecaries ſhop it profiteth nothyng: No more (ſaid he) coulde the benefite of Chriſtes Death healpe mée: becauſe, though I knew the medicyne good, I did not applie it vnto my Soule helth:<note place="margin">Storyes yeares were many and euill ſpent.</note> But now that it hath pleaſed Almightye God to call mée to accompt of my .lxvij. yeres, which now muſt haue an end, and this corrupt body muſt féele a temporall puniſſhement, for
<pb facs="tcp:25619:11"/> my ſinnes haue deſerued it (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) I am now come to the proofe of this Medicine.</p>
               <p>Dauid, when he had commytted Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterie with Barſabe the wyfe of Vrias (whoſe Huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo he cauſed to be put in the Front of the Battell, and ſo was he murthered:) he for that treſpaſſe felt a temporall puniſhment by the loſſe of the life of his ſon, which he loued tenderly.</p>
               <p>Alſo, when he nombred his people, he greatly diſpleaſed God: And for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and tranſgreſſion, he felt a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall payne: and choyce was geuen vnto him from aboue, to chooſe one of theſe .iij temporall and bodily punyſhments: that is to ſaye: Thrée daies Peſtilence: the Sworde, that is to ſaye, bloody Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell .vij. yeres: or Famyne .vij. yeres.</p>
               <p>And he thought to chooſe the leaſt: and he choſe thrée daies Peſtilence. But this Scourge tooke away an infinite nombre of his ſubiectes. So nowe as my ſinnes deſerue a temporall payne, whiche here haue an ende, euen in this fleſh: I am of the ſame minde that the Prophet Dauid was: And with hym I agrée ſaiyng. <hi>Inuoco te Domine. &amp;c.</hi> Lord I call vpon thée in this day of my trouble, heare mée O Lorde out of thy dwellynge place. &amp;c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25619:12"/>
               <p>But nowe to ſpeake a litle of my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment: when I was at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I alleaged in my plea that I was no Subiect of this Realme,<note place="margin">Hys hand is to the contrary.</note> as I did like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe before the Quenes Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, Sir Thomas Wroth, Maiſter Thomas Wilbraham late Recorder of the Citie of London, M. Peter Oſborne, Maiſter Marſhe, and M. Doctor Wattes: where the Recorder of London made lyke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde as was demaunded of mée at Weſtminſter: and that was whether I was borne in Englande, or no? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I aunſwered I was.</p>
               <p>Then ſayde he, it foloweth that you are and ought to continue the Quenes faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full ſubiect.<note place="margin">I lye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners.</note> Wherunto I replied then as I do now, ſaiyng: I am ſworne to the noble Kyng, Defendour of the auncient Catholique Faith, Kyng Philip Kyng of Spaine: And he is ſworne again by a ſolempne and corporall Othe, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and defende the Vniuerſitie of Louaine,<note place="margin">Storyes hand is to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of hys voluntarye confeſſion.</note> wherof I am a member, and therfore no ſubiect of this Realme, no yet ſubiect to any Lawes therof:</p>
               <p>For it is well knowen, that I depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Realme beynge fréelye licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therunto by the Quéene, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted mée an abiect and caſtawaye,
<pb facs="tcp:25619:12"/> and I came not hether agayne of myne owne accorde: but I was betrayed.</p>
               <p>And although I had an inckelyng ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mée before of ſuch a thing pretended towardes mée,<note place="margin">Story was not betrayed, but by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to be cut off, as a naughty &amp; corrupt member.</note> yet I coulde not ſhun nor eſcape it: For ſure it was God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made dym myne vnderſtandyng, and blynded myne eyes, ſo that I could not perceyue it. But holye writ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth mée to loue my enemies, &amp; here I forgeue them fréely with all my hart, beſéechyng God that they take no harme for mée in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countrey, I would be right ſorye they ſhould, although they betrayed me.</p>
               <p>I trauayled with them from Ship to Ship, by the ſpace of eight daies and miſtruſted no perill to be at hand vntyll I was clapt faſt vnder the Hatches.</p>
               <p>But ſure, ſure: it was God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wrought it: Yea, and although I was accompted a Poller of the Englyſſhe men of your countrey: I ſtand now here before God, and by the death I ſhall die, I had neuer out of any Ship more then two Péeces of Golde, and fortie Dallers that was laid in my hand.</p>
               <p>But once agayne, to my arraignme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where there were certain Letters laid to my charge, wherin I ſhould go about to
<pb facs="tcp:25619:13"/> prouoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nortons, the Neuiles &amp; oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to rebell, I neuer ment it: Yet wyll I diſcharge my conſcience fréely &amp; frankly and tell you trueth.<note place="margin">Here Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye before he was war, hath tolde you that he was a ranke Traytour.</note> There was a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for a lyke matter ſent into Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, which I wrote with myne owne hande: But it conteyned a Prouiſo, wherin the Quéene of England and her Dominions were excepted.</p>
               <p>There are yet two thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to talke of: namely, for that ther are here preſent a great nombre of Youth: And I woulde to God I might ſaye or ſpeke that which might bring all men to the vnitie of the Church: for there is but one Church, one Flocke and one Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde: If I could this do, I would think my ſelfe to haue wrought a good worke.</p>
               <p>The firſt Poinct toucheth my crueltie, wherwith I am ſore burdened: And the ſecond concerneth my Religion.</p>
               <p>As touchyng the firſt, there were thrée in Commiſſion, of the which I was one that might do leaſt, for I was the laſt of the thrée. And thoughe I might by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion aſſaye to cauſe them to reuoke the articles that they had maintayned, and to confeſſe the preſence, wherin I
<pb facs="tcp:25619:13"/> ſtande: Ye know that he that chydeth, is not worthy to bée condemned for figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng: No more am I worthy to be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cruell for chydynge: It was the Biſſhop that pronounced the Sentence <hi>Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municamus,</hi> and againſt that I could not do, for I was one of the Layetie.</p>
               <p>Yet often times the Biſſhop to whom I was Serua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was bold with mée when he had ſo many Priſoners that he could not well beſtow them. For at one time the Lorde Riche, ſent him out of Eſſex. xxviij. And at another time .xxiiij. Alſo at another time .xvi. and .xiiij. and ſome of them were ſent to mée, whiche I kepte in my Houſe with ſuche fare as I had prouided for my ſelfe and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylie, at myne owne coſt and charge.</p>
               <p>And to proue that I was not ſo cruell as I am reported to bée,<note place="margin">A prety tale, and it were long inough and true i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</note> let this one tale ſuffiſe: There were at one tyme .xxviij condempned to the Fire, and I moued the Deane of Paules to tender and pitie their eſtate, whiche after was Abbot of Weſtminſter, a very pitiful minded ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I thincke the moſte parte of you know him, it is M. Fecknam, and we went vp and perſwaded with them, and we fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them very tractable. And Maſter Feck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam and I laboured to the Lorde Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:25619:14"/> Poole, ſhewynge that they were.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Neſcientes qùid fecerunt.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>The Cardinall &amp; we did ſue together to the Quene, &amp; layd both the Swordes together, and ſo we obteyned pardon for them all, ſauynge an olde woman that dwelt aboute Paules Churchyard, ſhée would not conuert, and therfore ſhe was burned. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of them receyued abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucion, and that with al reuerence: ſerch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Regiſter and you ſhall finde it.</p>
               <p>Yea, &amp; it was my procurement that there ſhould be no more burnt in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for I ſawe well that it woulde not preuaile, and therfore we ſent them into odde corners into the countrey.</p>
               <p>Wherfore I pray you, name me not cruell, I would be loth to haue any ſuche ſlaunder to ron on mée. But ſith I dye in charitie, I pray you al of charitie to pray for mee, that God maye ſtrengthen mee with patience to ſuffer my death: to the whiche I yelde moſt wyllyngly.</p>
               <p>And here I make a peticion to you my frendes that woulde haue beſtowed any<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng on mée, I beſéeche you for charitie ſake, beſtow it yerely on my wife, who hath foure ſmall children, and God hath now taken me away that was her ſtaff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſtay: And now my Doughter We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton
<pb facs="tcp:25619:14"/> and her three chyldren are gone ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto her, and I know not how they ſhal do for foode, vnleſſe they go a beggynge f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m doore to doore for it: although in dede no Engliſh perſons do begge but of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, beyng helped by the Lady Dorm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Sir Franciſco: I haue good hope that you wyll be good vnto her, for ſhe is the faythfulleſt wife, the louyngeſt and conſtanteſt that euer man had. And twiſe we haue loſt all that euer we had, and nowe ſhe hath loſt mée to her great griefe I knowe.</p>
               <p>The ſecond poynct that I thought to ſpeke of, is concernyng my Religion, for that I know many are deſirous to know what faith I wyll dye in, the whiche I wyll briefely touch: I ſaye with Sainct Iherome that auncient father and piller of the old auncient, catholique, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke Churche grounded vpon the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es; Prophetes and Apoſtles, that in the ſame faith that I was borne in,<note place="margin">Which is not the church wherein S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome liued.</note> I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rpoſe to dye. And as the Arcke that Noe and his Famyly did poſſeſſe, figured the ſhip of Chriſtes Church, out of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hyp who ſoeuer is can not be ſaued. In tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhyp am I: Example. A ſhyp that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> toſſed on the floods is often in daunger
<pb facs="tcp:25619:15"/> of loſſe on the ſandes, and ſomtimes on the rocke. But when the men that are in the ſhip eſpye preſent peryll at hande, there is a Cockboat at the tayle of the ſhip, wherunto they flye for ſuccour: So likewiſe, I beynge in the Ship of Chriſt, once fell out of the ſame ſhip and was in preſent peryl and great danger. But then I folowynge the example of a good Maryner, tooke the Cockboat, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge to driue to lande: and at the laſt, beyng in the boat, I eſpied thrée Oares, that is to wit: Contricion, Confeſſion &amp; Abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And I held al theſe faſt, and euer ſence I haue continued in the ſhip of Chriſt, of whiche, the Apoſtle Peter is the guide and principall, &amp; in the faith catholike of my kynge I die.</p>
               <p>Then ſayd the Earle of Bedford, are you not the Quéenes ſubiect? No, ſayd Story, &amp; yet I do not exclude the Quene but I pray for her, her Counſaile and the Nobilitie of this Realme longe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. Then ſaid the Lorde Honſdon: Are you not the Quéenes Subiect, you were borne in Englande? Then ſayde Story: Euery man is frée borne, and he hath the whole face of the Earth before him to dwell &amp; abyde in where he liketh beſt: and if he can not lyue here, he may
<pb facs="tcp:25619:15"/> go els where. Then was there (as I thinke one of the Miniſters) hearyng him to make ſo light of our noble Quene and Countrey, demaunded of him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe were not next and immediatlye vnder God, Supreme head of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Englande and Irelande? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he aunſwered: I come not hether to diſpute, but if ſhée bée, ſhée is: my nay wyll not preuayle to proue it otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>And then they cryed, awaye with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arte: And ſo he was hanged according to his iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <head>
                  <hi>An Epilogue, or a briefe</hi> Concluſion, of the lyfe of the aforeſaid Iohn Story.</head>
               <p>THe aforeſaid Iohn Storie, beſide that he was an obſtinat Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt and a rancke Traitour, he was alſo in Quéene Maryes time, the cruelleſt ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant &amp; perſecutor of the innocent mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres and bleſſed profeſſors of Chriſt, that euer was to his power, ſithen that cruell tirant Nero. For his whole delectacion and pleaſure was, in racking, ſtockyng,
<pb facs="tcp:25619:16"/> whippyng, manaklyng and burnyng of innocents, without reſpect either of age, vertue, learnyng, weakenes of wyt, or of a ſimple boye, or childiſh wenche: and all was fiſh that came to the net.</p>
               <p>And he often and openly ſaide (in the herynge of many) in the time of Quéene Mary, that the burnynge of Heretiques (as he termed them) was to gentle a deth for they had too muche ſcope to prate and talke what they luſt: But ſayd he, if I lyue, I wyll haue a clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Cage of Iron made for them, with a doore in the ſide, lyke to the Braſen Bull of perillus, where they ſhalbe encloſed, and the doore made faſt, and the fire to be made vnder them. And then (ſaid he) they ſhall know what friyng is, and their mouthes ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſtopped from blowyng out their peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Doctrine. So that by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, it maye manifeſtly appéere, that there hath not ben a wickeder man to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde God, his Prince &amp; countrey, then he hath ben.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>¶God ſaue the Queene, and confounde her enemies.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>¶Séene and allowed. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:25619:16"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
